Julien Tourille - PhD Student

LIMSI
Building 508
Rue John von Neumann
Campus Universitaire d'Orsay
91405 ORSAY CEDEX
FRANCE

E-MAIL: julien.tourille@gmail.com

Website: https://jtourille.github.io



(last update: April 2018)

Current Position: PhD Student in Natural Language Processing

Since 2015 PhD in Computer Science, LIMSI, CNRS, Univ. Paris-Sud, Université Paris-Saclay

Topic Cross-Document Event Coreference in Electronic Health Records

Laboratory Laboratoire d'Informatique pour la Mécanique et les Sciences de l'Ingénieur

Advisors Xavier Tannier, Aurélie Névéol and Olivier Ferret

Description Important information for public health is locked in electronic patient records which are written in natural language. These records represent a considerable corpus, which grows by several hundreds of thousands of documents every year per hospital. The retrospective analysis of these records allows health professionals to obtain a concise view of the healthcare pathways within their institutions. It allows to compare effective patient care to clinical guidelines in order i) to evaluate the quality of the healthcare pathway, ii) to highlight the steps of the pathway where specific care should be provided and iii) to further improve the diagnosis process and the therapeutic approach. In my PhD dissertation, I propose to develop natural language processing methods adapted to the clinical language, which will facilitate the summarization of information regarding healthcare pathways in the context of

retrospective analyses.

Education

Since 2015 PhD in Computer Science, LIMSI, CNRS, Univ. Paris-Sud, Université Paris-Saclay

2014–2015 MSc (second year) - Natural Language Processing with a specialization in Research and Development, Paris Nanterre University, University of Paris III: Sor-

bonne Nouvelle, and INALCO | summa cum laude

2013-2014 MSc (first year) - Lexicography, Terminography et Automatic Corpus Processing,

University of Lille | summa cum laude

Doctoral Education

- 2018 Introduction to research ethics and integrity, Gif-sur-Yvette, France
- 2018 Professional careers outside academia, Orsay, France
- 2018 Open access publication and bibliometrics, Gif-sur-Yvette, France
- 2016 Lisbon Machine Learning School (LxMLS), Lisbonne, Portugal
- 2015 Teaching assistant basics, Saclay, France

Other Training

2017 Collaborative Institutional Training Initiative

- Curriculum Group: Human Research
- Course Learner Group: Group 1 Biomedical
- Stage: Stage 1 Basic Course
- Description: Biomedical Investigators and Key Personnel Who Interact With Subjects
- Completion date: April 13, 2017Expiration date: April 20, 2020

Publications

- [5] Julien Tourille, Olivier Ferret, Xavier Tannier, and Aurélie Névéol. "LIMSI-COT at SemEval-2017 Task 12: Neural Architecture for Temporal Information Extraction from Clinical Narratives". In: *Proceedings of the 11th International Workshop on Semantic Evaluation (SemEval 2017)*. Vancouver, Canada: Association for Computational Linguistics, Aug. 2017, pp. 597–602. URL: http://www.aclweb.org/anthology/S17-2098.
- [4] Julien Tourille, Olivier Ferret, Xavier Tannier, and Aurélie Névéol. "Neural Architecture for Temporal Relation Extraction: A Bi-LSTM Approach for Detecting Narrative Containers". In: *Proceedings of the 55th Conference of the Association for Computational Linguistics*. Vancouver, Canada: Association for Computational Linguistics, Aug. 2017, pp. 224–230. URL: http://aclweb.org/anthology/P17–2035.
- [3] Julien Tourille, Olivier Ferret, Xavier Tannier, and Aurélie Névéol. "Temporal information extraction from clinical text". In: *Proceedings of the 15th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics*. Valencia, Spain: Association for Computational Linguistics, Apr. 2017, pp. 739–745. URL: http://www.aclweb.org/anthology/E17-2117.
- [2] Julien Tourille, Olivier Ferret, Aurélie Névéol, and Xavier Tannier. "Extraction de relations temporelles dans des dossiers électroniques patient". In: Actes de la Conférence Traitement Automatique des Langues Naturelles (TALN 2016). Paris, France: Association pour le Traitement Automatique des Langues, July 2016, pp. 459–466. URL: https://jep-taln2016.limsi.fr/actes/Actes%20JTR-2016/Papers/T90.pdf.
- [1] Julien Tourille, Olivier Ferret, Aurélie Névéol, and Xavier Tannier. "LIMSI-COT at SemEval-2016 Task 12: Temporal relation identification using a pipeline of classifiers". In: *Proceedings of the 10th International Workshop on Semantic Evaluation (SemEval-2016)*. San Diego, California: Association for Computational Linguistics, June 2016, pp. 1136–1142. URL: http://www.aclweb.org/anthology/S16–1175.

Talks, Seminars, Posters and Demonstrations

Jan. 2018	Doctoral seminar Location: LIMSI, Orsay, France Title: Yet Another SEquence
	Tagger (YASET)
Dec. 2017	System demonstration at Journée e-santé Location: NanoInnov, Palaiseau, France

System: Yet Another SEquence Tagger (YASET)

Nov. 2017 Presentation at OpenHealth seminar | Location: OpenHealth Institute, Paris, France Topic: Détection automatique de la coréférence événementielle dans les dossiers patients électroniques

Jun. 2017 Doctoral seminar | Location: LIMSI, Orsay, France | Title: Temporal Analysis in **Electronic Health Records**

Presentation at THYME group bi-weekly meeting | Location: Boston Children's Apr. 2017 Hospital, Boston, USA | Topic: Temporal Information Extraction from Clinical Narratives

May 2016 Presentation at LIMSI PhD day | Location: LIMSI, CNRS, Saclay, France Topic: Cross-Document Event Coreference in Electronic Health Records

Poster at Digicosme Research Days | Location: CentraleSupélec, Saclay, France Apr. 2016 Topic: Cross-Document Event Coreference in Electronic Health Records

Other Research Experience

2015	Master'	s thesis	in	Natural	Language	Processing
------	---------	----------	----	---------	----------	------------

Automatic Detection of Epistemic Modality in Biomedical Texts

MoDyCo Laboratory (CNRS UMR 7114), Nanterre, France Laboratory

Advisor Delphine Battistelli

Topics - Modelization of the epistemic modality in biomedical scientific texts written in english.

- Conception and development of a modality tagger.

Research Internship in Natural Language Processing 2014

ITEC Laboratory, Kortrijk, Belgium Laboratory

Hans Paulussen Advisor

Topics - Evaluation and optimization of a named entity recognition system developed for the IReadPlus project.

- Training and optimization of a Part-Of-Speech Tagger using the GRACE tagset.
- Conception and development of monitoring tools for the laboratory NLP pipeline.

Research Stays

Research stay at the Natural Language Processing Laboratory of the Boston Children's Hospital, Boston, USA | April 2017-May 2017

Awards

- 2017 Selected for the "Best of SemEval-2017" session, SemEval Workshop, Vancouver, Canada
- 2016 Selected for the "Best of SemEval-2016" session, SemEval Workshop, San Diego, USA

Funding

- 2015–2018 3-year PhD funding from the excellence laboratory center (labex) DigiCosme
 - 2017 Grant from the OpenHealth Institute for a research stay at the Natural Language Processing Laboratory of the Boston's Children Hospital, Boston, USA

Teaching Experience

2017–2018 University Institute of Technology, Univ. Paris-Sud, Université Paris-Saclay

- 1^{st} year undergraduate in computer science: **digital documents and interfaces** (1^{st} term) | Teaching assistant to Benjamin Hellouin
- 2^{nd} year undergraduate in computer science: advanced database techniques (1st term) | Teaching assistant to Nicolas Férey
- 1^{st} year undergraduate in computer science: **object oriented design** (2^{nd} term) | Teaching assistant to Chantal Reynaud

2016–2017 University Institute of Technology, Univ. Paris-Sud, Université Paris-Saclay

- 1^{st} year undergraduate in computer science: digital documents and interfaces (1^{st} term) | Teaching assistant to Veronique Moriceau, Sylvie Delaët and Laurence Salvator
- 2^{nd} year undergraduate in computer science: advanced database techniques (1st term) | Teaching assistant to Nicolas Férey
- 2^{nd} year undergraduate in computer science: **software production** (1st term) Teaching assistant to Ana Lopez

2015–2016 University Institute of Technology, Univ. Paris-Sud, Université Paris-Saclay

- 2^{nd} year undergraduate in computer science: advanced database techniques (1st term) | Teaching assistant to Nicolas Férey
- 1^{st} year undergraduate in computer science: **object oriented design** (2^{nd} term) | Teaching assistant to Chantal Reynaud

Other Activities

- Reviewer for AMIA, SemEval, ACL and BMC Bioinformatics
- Organization of the 2016 edition of the LIMSI PhD day